<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<document>

    <header>

        <fileDesc>

            <titleStmt>
                <title>Text encoding of professional library organizations' statements in response
                    to racism at the 2019 ALA Midwinter Meeting</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared by Cara Key</resp>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>

            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Published in GitHub: https://github.com/carakey/alamw19-statements.</p>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Statements were originally posted on various platforms, including organization
                    web sites, ALA Connect, and social media sites; the specific web location for
                    each is identified in the statement metadata in the first generation (F1) of
                    this XML document.</p>
                <p>The document "Statements from ALA Units and Affiliates on Racism within ALA"
                    posted by Diedre Conkling on ALA Connect on Feb 7 was used as the source of the
                    statements list. Source:
                    https://docs.google.com/document/d/13IQd6EZCN5Z670y5G-2bpkUMnqpOE9KeWv0YD2ig6os</p>
            </sourceDesc>

        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>

            <projectDesc>
                <p>This project is an encoding of statements issued by ALA, its divisions, sections,
                    and other affiliates in response to the incidents of racism and harassment that
                    occurred at ALA's 2019 Midwinter Meeting. The text has been encoded through a
                    combination of manual markup and iterative XSL transformations, and the
                    resulting data supports qualitative content analysis using XQuery.</p>
            </projectDesc>

            <samplingDecl>
                <p>The following items, included in Conkling's list, were not part of the project
                    for the reasons given: (1) ASERL: Statement from Yolanda Cooper, ASERL Board
                    President, 2/5/19: http://www.aserl.org/; Reason for omission: Statement is no
                    longer available at this link, and could not be found with a reasonable amount
                    of searching. (2) GODORT Statement from the GODORT Steering Committee, 2/4/19:
                    https://bit.ly/2E5oJh; Reason for omission: Statement is no longer available at
                    this link, and could not be found with a reasonable amount of searching. (3) ALA
                    President announces future EDI Efforts, 2/8/19: https://bit.ly/2RNffvf; Reason
                    for omission: Not an explicit response to ALAMW 2019 incidents. (4) Educopia
                    Institute: Making Community Spaces Safer..., 2/8/19: https://bit.ly/2BxFjoE;
                    Reason for omission: Not produced by an ALA unit/affiliate.</p>
            </samplingDecl>

        </encodingDesc>

    </header>


    <text>
        <group>

            <text
                source="http://www.ala.org/news/member-news/2019/01/ala-executive-board-releases-statement-regarding-incident-council-forum">

                <front>
                    <docTitle focus="incidents" context="alamw19">ALA Executive Board releases
                        statement regarding incident at Council Forum</docTitle>
                    <div type="pub_note">
                        <l>For Immediate Release</l>
                        <l>Thu, 01/31/2019</l>
                    </div>
                    <div type="contact">
                        <head>Contact:</head>
                        <l>Steve Zalusky</l>
                        <l>Communications Specialist</l>
                        <l>Communications and Marketing Office</l>
                        <l>American Library Association</l>
                        <l>(312) 280-1546</l>
                        <l>szalusky@ala.org</l>
                    </div>
                    <div type="pub_note">
                        <p>The ALA Executive Board has released the following statement regarding a
                            recent incident during Council Forum at the ALA Midwinter Meeting &amp;
                            Exhibits in Seattle.</p>
                    </div>
                </front>

                <body>

                    <p>We should not – and do not – accept harassment, bullying or discrimination of
                        any kind in our profession or the work of <entity type="organization"
                            identity="self">our Association</entity>. These behaviors go against our
                        values. Violations to our code of conduct will not be tolerated.</p>

                    <p>We established a code of conduct because we take the responsibility of being
                        respectful to each other very seriously.</p>

                    <p>We send our sincere apologies to <entity type="person" identity="named"
                            >Councilor April Hathcock</entity> for what she went through at <entity
                            type="event">Council Forum</entity>, which is unacceptable and doesn’t
                        align with our core values.</p>

                    <p><entity type="person" identity="implied">The ALA attorney</entity> and
                            <entity type="person" identity="implied">President-Elect</entity> met
                        with <entity type="person" identity="named">April Hathcock</entity> in
                            <entity type="place">the Council meeting room</entity> shortly before
                            <entity type="event">Council III</entity> to share some nonpublic
                        information about events after the incident in question. <entity
                            type="organization" identity="self">ALA</entity> leaders deeply regrets
                        any distress this caused; it was not the intent of <entity type="person"
                            identity="implied">the attorney</entity> or <entity type="organization"
                            identity="self">ALA</entity> to threaten <entity type="person"
                            identity="named">Ms Hathcock</entity> in any way.</p>

                    <p><entity type="person" identity="anonymous">The Councilor</entity> who
                        instigated the incident has resigned and the Executive Board has accepted
                        his resignation.</p>

                    <p>We also offer our sincere apologies to members who also experienced
                        violations of the code of conduct at <entity type="event">the Midwinter
                            meeting</entity>.</p>

                    <p>We want to recognize that this incident has caused a lot of hurt and we are
                        working diligently to ensure that at all <entity type="organization"
                            identity="self">ALA</entity> events participants are - and feel -
                        respected.  </p>

                    <p>The Executive Board will form a working group to look at <entity type="event"
                            >Council Forum</entity> and ways to make it a safer space up to its
                        continued viability.</p>

                    <p>We will review the current code of conduct complaint process to make it
                        stronger and more effective.</p>

                    <p>We will work on facilitated racial equity training for <entity type="event"
                            >Annual Conference</entity> during <entity type="event">Council
                            1</entity>; that training and the code of conduct will be built into
                            <entity type="organization">Council</entity> Orientation moving
                        forward.</p>

                    <p>In collaboration with the Office for Diversity, Literacy and Outreach
                        Services, we will coordinate online and in-person resources on equity,
                        diversity and inclusion for all members and for <entity type="organization"
                            identity="self">ALA</entity> staff members.</p>

                    <p><entity type="organization" identity="self">ALA</entity> and <entity
                            type="organization">its Divisions</entity> have developed resources<link
                            target="http://www.ala.org/aboutala/offices/diversity/edi"/> to embed
                        principles of equity, diversity and inclusion in the work library workers
                        do; see specifics for 2018 here<link
                            target="http://www.ala.org/aboutala/sites/ala.org.aboutala/files/content/diversity/EBD%2012.16_2018%20Recommendations.pdf"
                        />. Last October during <entity type="event">the 2018 Fall Executive Board
                            Meeting</entity>, the Executive Board voted to affirm that <entity
                            type="organization" identity="self">ALA</entity> will apply a social
                        justice framework to the <entity type="organization">ALA</entity> Strategic
                            Directions<link target="http://www.ala.org/aboutala/strategicplan"/> for
                        the next three-to-five years in the areas of Advocacy, Information Policy,
                        Professional and Leadership Development, and Equity, Diversity and
                        Inclusion. We are building on the 2019 <entity type="program">President's
                            Program</entity> about "White Fragility"<link
                            target="https://americanlibrariesmagazine.org/blogs/the-scoop/robin-diangelo-gets-real-racism/"
                        />.</p>

                    <p>This work can be messy, it takes time, but the Executive Board strives to
                        create a better association every day. We ask for your collaboration to help
                        us break through the systems of oppression and do the right thing at the
                        right time, each time, as it should be done.</p>

                </body>

                <back>
                    <div type="tags">
                        <head>Tags</head>
                        <l>Council</l>
                    </div>
                </back>

            </text>

            <text source="http://www.apalaweb.org/apala-statement-against-racism-and-harassment">

                <front>
                    <docTitle focus="racism" context="unspecified">APALA statement against racism
                        and harassment</docTitle>
                    <div type="pub_note">
                        <l>For Immediate Release</l>
                        <l>Thursday, 01/31/2019</l>
                    </div>
                    <div type="contact">
                        <head>CONTACT:</head>
                        <l>Jaena Rae Cabrera</l>
                        <l>Co-Chair, Media and Publicity Committee</l>
                        <l>Asian/Pacific American Librarians Association</l>
                        <l>communications@apalaweb.org</l>
                    </div>
                    <div type="pub_note">
                        <l>APALA releases statement against racism and harassment</l>
                    </div>
                </front>


                <body>
                    <p><entity type="organization" identity="self">The Asian Pacific American
                            Librarians Association (APALA)</entity> expresses its support for the
                        Black people and people of color who experienced racism and harassment at
                            <entity type="event">the 2019 ALA Midwinter Meeting</entity> in <entity
                            type="place">Seattle, WA</entity>. These incidents are not singular or
                        isolated, and, coupled with the recent racial profiling and discrimination
                        of Black future librarians at a university library in <entity type="place"
                            >the District of Columbia</entity><link
                            target="https://www.theroot.com/video-librarian-calls-cops-on-student-for-brazen-attem-1829940301"
                        /> and a public library in <entity type="place">Texas</entity><link
                            target="https://abc13.com/society/police-called-on-black-grad-student-at-west-u-library/4689993/"
                        />, illustrates that there is much work to do to address systemic
                        discrimination, bias, power, and white privilege in our profession. While
                        the <entity type="program">ALA’s President’s Program</entity> at <entity
                            type="event">Midwinter</entity> was on white fragility, and <entity
                            type="organization">ALA Council</entity> often passes resolutions with
                        statements that purportedly support marginalized communities, <entity
                            type="organization">ALA</entity> itself as a member organization is
                        frequently not a safe space for BIPOC; and <entity type="organization"
                            identity="self">APALA</entity> calls on <entity type="organization"
                            >ALA</entity> to formally investigate some of the incidents that
                        occurred during <entity type="event">the ALA Midwinter Meeting</entity>.</p>

                    <p><entity type="organization" identity="self">APALA</entity>, one of the five
                        ethnic affiliates of <entity type="organization">the American Library
                            Association</entity>, is committed to “advancing social justice and
                        providing opportunities for dialogue” and we strongly denounce these types
                        of behavior, which create toxic environments for people of color. <entity
                            type="organization" identity="self">APALA</entity> acknowledges the
                        complexity of intersectional identities and how multiple systems of
                        oppression such as racism, sexism, classism, ableism and heterosexism (among
                        others) overlap and compound on the individual, and advocates for
                        prioritizing the experiences and voices of marginalized groups, and engaging
                        in difficult dialogues in order to create a more just, equitable, diverse,
                        and inclusive organization.</p>

                    <p><entity type="organization" identity="self">APALA</entity> calls for <entity
                            type="organization">the American Library Association</entity> to uphold
                        its core organizational values of  “ethics, professionalism, and integrity,”
                        to commit to its key areas of diversity that are “…a fundamental value of
                        the association and its members,” and to follow through on its commitment to
                        engage with diversity in deeper ways. <entity type="organization"
                            identity="self">APALA</entity> calls for <entity type="organization">the
                            American Library Association</entity> to engage with the five
                        ethnic-affiliates of <entity type="organization">AILA</entity>, <entity
                            type="organization" identity="self">APALA</entity>, <entity
                            type="organization">BCALA</entity>, <entity type="organization"
                            >CALA</entity>, and <entity type="organization">REFORMA</entity> to
                        create meaningful and purposeful change through discussion and action, in
                        order to make the profession more inclusive.</p>

                </body>

                <back>
                    <div type="pub_note">
                        <p>On behalf of the APALA Executive Board, by Paolo P. Gujilde, and approved
                            by members of the APALA Executive Board, Alanna Aiko Moore, Dora T. Ho,
                            Annie Pho, Peter Spyers-Duran, Lana Adlawan, Jaena Rae Cabrera, Rose L.
                            Chou, Anchalee (Joy) Panigabutra-Roberts and Buenaventura Basco. </p>

                        <p>Note: Based on the feedback of APALA members, this statement was edited
                            to show the importance of specifically naming anti-Blackness, to
                            emphasize that the discrimination that Black people face is very
                            different from the experiences of non-Black POC.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="about">
                        <p>Founded in 1980, the Asian/Pacific American Librarians Association
                            (APALA) is a 501(c)3 non-profit organization. All donations to APALA are
                            tax deductible and support our work for library services, programs,
                            scholarships, awards, and grants related to library services benefiting
                            Asian/Pacific Americans and Asian/Pacific American librarians.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="tags">
                        <l>Tagged ALA Midwinter, harassment, racism</l>
                    </div>
                </back>

            </text>

            <text source="https://www.acrl.ala.org/acrlinsider/archives/17145">

                <front>
                    <docTitle focus="racism" context="profession">ACRL Board Statement Against
                        Racism, Harassment, and Discrimination in the Profession</docTitle>
                    <div type="pub_note">
                        <l>January 31, 2019 * ACRL Board of Directors</l>
                    </div>
                    <div type="tags">
                        <l>Equity, Diversity, and Inclusion</l>
                    </div>
                </front>

                <body>
                    <p>The <entity type="organization" identity="self">Association of College &amp;
                            Research Libraries (ACRL)</entity> Board of Directors is aware that
                            <entity type="event">ALA Midwinter</entity> attendees have reported
                        experiencing violations of the conference Code of Conduct, including
                        incidents of racism, harassment, and discrimination. We laud the strength of
                        those who have shared their experiences to draw needed attention to
                        violations, and we abhor the systemic inequities in our profession that have
                        normalized discriminatory, harassing, and racist behaviors.</p>

                    <p>As a division of <entity type="organization">ALA</entity>, we are aware that
                            <entity type="organization" identity="self">ACRL</entity> also has work
                        to do to address systemic racism and oppressive practices within <entity
                            type="organization" identity="self">the Association</entity>. We
                        recognize that <entity type="organization" identity="self">ACRL</entity> is
                        not as representative as it needs to be. <entity type="organization"
                            identity="self">ACRL</entity> has a core commitment to Equity,
                        Diversity, and Inclusion<link
                            target="https://www.acrl.ala.org/acrlinsider/archives/15380"/> and
                        recognizes the urgency of taking steps to create a responsive association
                        that empowers all of its members. As part of our commitment, we have
                        arranged anti-bias training for leaders and trainers within <entity
                            type="organization" identity="self">ACRL</entity> and funded additional
                            <entity type="program">Spectrum Scholarships</entity> for colleagues of
                        color to join and thrive in the profession. We expect our leaders and
                        members to be courageous in speaking against harassment or bullying behavior
                        when they witness it.</p>

                    <p>Our commitment to a more equitable, inclusive, and diverse association leads
                        us to strongly urge <entity type="organization">ALA</entity> to carry out
                        the work it has promised to do in its statement<link
                            target="http://www.ala.org/news/member-news/2019/01/ala-executive-board-releases-statement-regarding-incident-council-forum"
                        /> and to set up town hall sessions with <entity type="organization"
                            >Council</entity>, the Executive Board, and the general membership, and
                        to seriously reflect on enacting our professional values. Our profession
                        needs to talk about the way that racism and systems that privilege whiteness
                        have permeated our profession and our professional events. The <entity
                            type="organization" identity="self">ACRL</entity> Board, Conference
                        planners, and staff will be reviewing plans for <entity type="event">the
                            ACRL 2019 Conference</entity><link target="https://conference.acrl.org/"
                        /> in <entity type="place">Cleveland</entity> to ensure that it is a safe
                        and welcoming place for all.</p>

                    <p>This work is critical. We do it in service of building a more inclusive and
                        equitable association and profession, and more inclusive and equitable
                        libraries for our communities. We hope that all <entity type="organization"
                            identity="self">ACRL</entity> members will reaffirm the Board’s
                        commitment to being advocates for our colleagues and advancing social
                        justice in our communities and association.</p>
                </body>

            </text>

            <text source="https://www.reforma.org/statement-against-racism">

                <front>
                    <docTitle focus="racism" context="profession">REFORMA Statement Against Racism
                        and Discrimination in the Library Profession</docTitle>
                </front>

                <body>
                    <p><entity type="organization" identity="self">REFORMA, the National Association
                            to Promote Library &amp; Information Services to Latinos and the Spanish
                            Speaking,</entity> has learned that various conference attendees
                        conveyed experiencing inappropriate and unacceptable behavior, including
                        displays of racism and discrimination, at <entity type="event">the 2019 ALA
                            Midwinter Meeting &amp; Exhibits</entity> in <entity type="place"
                            >Seattle, WA</entity>.</p>

                    <p>An ethnic affiliate of <entity type="organization">the American Library
                            Association (ALA)</entity>, <entity type="organization" identity="self"
                            >REFORMA</entity> is an association committed to supporting the
                        academic, professional, and personal efforts of <entity
                            type="protected_group">the Latinx community</entity>. It is
                        disheartening to learn that as we near our 50th anniversary as an
                        organization, we are still dealing with micro and macro aggressions that
                        make the library profession difficult for many people of color to
                        navigate.</p>

                    <p>In working with and for <entity type="protected_group">the Latinx
                            community</entity> we are cognizant of the systemic racism that affects
                        the lives of marginalized individuals and acknowledge that, while people of
                        color may reach leadership positions, we cannot dismiss the hostility and
                        inequity that comes with being a person of color in a predominantly white
                        profession, as well as the ways oppression impacts all minority groups.</p>

                    <p><entity type="organization" identity="self">REFORMA</entity> urges <entity
                            type="organization">the American Library Association</entity> to address
                        racism and discrimination in the profession, be it at the institutional
                        level or at professional development convenings. As a beacon for information
                        that is viewed globally, <entity type="organization">ALA</entity> must be
                        the foundation for inclusion and respect for all. We ask that <entity
                            type="organization">ALA</entity> take action, and support librarians of
                        color who experience deliberate or unconscious discrimination, by taking all
                        accusations or concerns regarding racism seriously. It requires further
                        investigation and is a dialogue that must expand upon the program on 'White
                        Fragility'.</p>

                    <p><entity type="organization" identity="self">REFORMA</entity> stands with
                        individuals who have been seen as anything other than their authentic selves
                        recognizing that discrimination finds roots in all marginalized communities
                        and across intersections of identity. We must not forget that while
                        libraries are repositories and hubs for information and resources, they are
                        also the cornerstone of the human condition where social justice plays a
                        role in aiding in the quality of life for all.</p>
                </body>

                <back>
                    <div type="about">
                        <p>To learn more about REFORMA’s mission, visit reforma.org<link
                                target="https://www.reforma.org/"/></p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="pub_note">
                        <p>On behalf of the REFORMA Executive Board by David Lopez, REFORMA Western
                            Region Chapter Representative &amp; ALA Councilor-at-Large</p>
                        <p>Approved by members of the REFORMA Executive Board: Madeline Peña Feliz,
                            Kenny Garcia, Tess Tobin, Ana Campos, Gloria Grover, Patricia
                            Valdovinos, Nicanor Diaz, Manny Figueroa</p>
                        <p>January 29, 2019</p>
                    </div>
                </back>

            </text>

            <text source="https://ailanet.org/aila-statement-against-racism-and-harassment">

                <front>
                    <docTitle focus="racism" context="unspecified">AILA Statement Against Racism and
                        Harassment</docTitle>
                    <div type="pub_note">
                        <l>February 1, 2019</l>
                    </div>
                </front>

                <body>
                    <p><entity type="organization" identity="self">The American Indian Library
                            Association</entity> stands with the individuals who experienced racism
                        and discrimination at <entity type="event">the 2019 ALA Midwinter Meeting
                            &amp; Exhibits</entity> in <entity type="place">Seattle, WA</entity>. We
                        stand with those who preserve and celebrate all cultures. Racism and
                        discrimination dishonor every culture.</p>

                    <p>As an ethnic affiliate of <entity type="organization">the American Library
                            Association (ALA)</entity>, <entity type="organization" identity="self"
                            >AILA</entity> is a membership action group that addresses the
                        library-related needs of <entity type="protected_group">American Indians and
                            Alaska Natives</entity>. <entity type="organization" identity="self"
                            >AILA</entity> is committed to promoting true representations of <entity
                            type="protected_group">American Indian</entity> cultures, languages, and
                        values. As <entity type="organization" identity="self">AILA</entity> reaches
                        its 40th anniversary, we strongly support librarians of color. We urge
                            <entity type="organization">the American Library Association</entity> to
                        address racism and discrimination in the profession at the institutional
                        level and at all professional development meetings.</p>

                    <p><entity type="organization" identity="self">The American Indian Library
                            Association</entity> joins our fellow ethnic affiliates, <entity
                            type="organization">APALA</entity>, <entity type="organization"
                            >BCALA</entity>, <entity type="organization">CALA</entity>, and <entity
                            type="organization">REFORMA</entity>, and offers our support to <entity
                            type="organization">the American Library Association</entity> in order
                        to realize <entity type="organization">ALA</entity>’s future. <entity
                            type="organization" identity="self">AILA</entity> appreciates the work
                        of <entity type="person" identity="named">Jody Gray, Director</entity> of
                        the Office for Diversity, Literacy &amp; Outreach Services for <entity
                            type="organization">American Library Association</entity> and is
                        committed to working with <entity type="organization">ALA</entity> to
                        address racism, bias, and discrimination in our communities.</p>
                </body>

                <back>
                    <div type="about">
                        <p>To learn more about AILA’s mission, visit ailanet.org<link
                                target="http://ailanet.org/"/></p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="contact">
                        <head>CONTACT:</head>
                        <l>American Indian Library Association</l>
                        <l>Executive Board</l>
                        <l>ailawebsite@gmail.com</l>
                    </div>
                </back>

            </text>

            <text
                source="https://www.facebook.com/notes/bcala-the-black-caucus-of-the-american-library-association/statement-in-response-to-incidents-at-ala-midwinter-2019/2250815475243894/">

                <front>
                    <docTitle focus="incidents" context="alamw19">Statement in Response to Incidents
                        at ALA Midwinter 2019</docTitle>
                    <div type="pub_note">
                        <l>BCALA - The Black Caucus of the American Library Association * Thursday,
                            January 31, 2019</l>
                    </div>
                </front>

                <body>
                    <p><entity type="organization" identity="self">The Black Caucus of the American
                            Library Association (BCALA)</entity> thanks <entity type="organization"
                            >REFORMA</entity>, <entity type="organization">ALA</entity> Executive
                        Board, <entity type="organization">APALA</entity> and <entity
                            type="organization">AILA</entity> for crafting such appropriate
                        statements against racism and discrimination in the Library profession, in
                        response to conference attendees receiving inappropriate and unacceptable
                        behavior during <entity type="event">the Midwinter meeting</entity>. We are
                        in agreement with the expressions of concern and call for <entity
                            type="organization">ALA</entity> to step up in leading our association
                        and its members through the task of understanding, valuing differences and
                        communicating respectfully. Education with conversation is an essential
                        component to a journey of complete inclusion with fair and equal treatment
                        for all. <entity type="organization" identity="self">BCALA</entity> stands
                        committed to these values and welcomes the opportunity to collaborate with
                        the other affiliates and <entity type="organization">ALA</entity> to promote
                        and provide cultural sensitivity training.</p>
                </body>

                <back>
                    <div type="pub_note">
                        <p>On behalf of the BCALA Executive Board by Richard E. Ashby, Jr.,
                            President Black Caucus American Library Association. </p>
                        <p>Approved by members of the BCALA Executive Board: Shauntee Burns-Simpson,
                            Denyvetta Davis, Elisa Garcia, Cherese McKnight</p>
                    </div>
                </back>

            </text>

            <text source="http://libr.org/srrt/index.php">

                <front>
                    <docTitle focus="violations" context="alamw19">SRRT Statement on Racist
                        Aggression at ALA Conferences</docTitle>
                    <div type="pub_note">
                        <l>February 2, 2019</l>
                    </div>
                </front>

                <body>
                    <p>We at <entity type="organization" identity="self">the Social Responsibilities
                            Round Table</entity> condemn strongly the incidents of racist behavior
                        that have been reported at the most recent <entity type="event">American
                            Library Association Midwinter Meeting</entity>, the best known of which
                        is the verbal attack on <entity type="person" identity="named"
                            >Councilor-at-Large April Hathcock</entity> at <entity type="event">a
                            Council Forum on Monday evening, January 28, 2019</entity>. Other
                        attendees have reported acts of aggression, exclusion, and racial profiling
                        at this and previous conferences. This ongoing pattern of exclusionary
                        behavior is absolutely unacceptable and completely contrary to our values as
                        both a profession and an organization.</p>

                    <p>We fully support the action steps outlined by <entity type="person"
                            identity="named">April Hathcock</entity> (1)<link
                            target="https://aprilhathcock.wordpress.com/2019/01/30/alamw-what-happened-and-what-should-happen-next/"
                        />. We note that in a statement issued on Thursday, January 31st, the
                            <entity type="organization">ALA</entity> Executive Board has made at
                        least some steps towards each of these requests. We urge <entity
                            type="organization">the ALA Council</entity> and the <entity
                            type="organization">ALA</entity> Executive Board to continue to move
                        forward in addressing the concerns of its members. Further, we request that,
                        in the interest of transparency and accountability, the <entity
                            type="organization">ALA</entity> Conference Services Office give regular
                        accounts of incidents of racism, homophobia, and other bigotry reported at
                        conferences.</p>

                    <p>The change we must see goes beyond simple "diversity": we must take a truly
                        progressive approach to championing anti-racism in our actions. If we are to
                        live up to the directive in the <entity type="organization">ALA</entity>
                        mission statement to "enhance learning and ensure access to information for
                        all," (2)<link target="http://www.ala.org/aboutala/missionpriorities%22"/>
                        we must do better. We must protect each other, we must respect each other,
                        and we must value each other. If we will not do these things for each other,
                        we cannot do them for our communities.</p>
                </body>

                <back>
                    <div type="contact">
                        <head>Contact:</head>
                        <l>Charles E. Kratz,</l>
                        <l>SRRT Action Council Coordinator</l>
                        <l>Weinberg Memorial Library</l>
                        <l>The University of Scranton</l>
                        <l>Scranton, PA 18510</l>
                        <l>570-941-4008 (Work)</l>
                    </div>
                </back>

            </text>

            <text source="https://www.glbtrt.ala.org/news/archives/4046">

                <front>
                    <docTitle focus="racism" context="unspecified">GLBT Round Table Statement
                        against Racism, Harassment, and Bullying</docTitle>
                    <div type="pub_note">
                        <l>by GLTBT News</l>
                    </div>
                    <div type="tags">
                        <l>GLBT News</l>
                        <l>Midwinter Meetings</l>
                    </div>
                </front>

                <body>
                    <p><entity type="organization" identity="self">The Gay, Lesbian, Bisexual, and
                            Transgender Round Table (GLBTRT)</entity> expresses its support and
                        stands in solidarity with <entity type="organization">ALA</entity> members
                        who have experienced racism, discrimination, and microaggressions within our
                        association, most recently, but certainly not only at <entity type="event"
                            >the 2019 ALA Midwinter Meeting</entity>. We are categorically opposed
                        to the harassment and aggression toward people of color in our profession
                        and our professional community, online and in person.</p>

                    <p><entity type="organization" identity="self">The GLBTRT</entity> is also
                        deeply concerned and disturbed to have been made aware of past instances of
                        homophobic and bullying remarks directed at <entity type="person"
                            identity="anonymous">a GLBTRT member on Council</entity> during <entity
                            type="event">a discussion on a Council resolution</entity>. We are
                        equally categorically opposed to the harassment, bullying, and
                        discrimination of our members, and people of all <entity
                            type="protected_group">sexual orientations</entity> and <entity
                            type="protected_group">gender identities</entity>.</p>

                    <p>Recognizing and celebrating the wonderful diversity and intersectionality of
                        voices and rich, lived experiences within the library community, and of the
                        initial steps taken by <entity type="organization">ALA</entity> to address
                        issues of equity, diversity, and inclusion through the efforts of the Office
                        of Diversity, Literacy, and Outreach Services (ODLOS), <entity
                            type="organization" identity="self">the GLBTRT</entity> acknowledges
                        there is much more work to be done, and will continue to help create safe
                        spaces for these voices to be heard and play an active role in our
                        organization. In conjunction with ODLOS, and in solidarity with <entity
                            type="organization">ALA</entity>’s five ethnic affiliates, <entity
                            type="organization">the American Indian Library Association</entity>,
                            <entity type="organization">the Asian Pacific American Librarians
                            Association</entity>, <entity type="organization">the Black Caucus of
                            the American Library Association</entity>, <entity type="organization"
                            >the Chinese American Librarians Association</entity>, and <entity
                            type="organization">the Association to Promote Library and Information
                            Services to Latinos and the Spanish Speaking</entity>, <entity
                            type="organization" identity="self">the GLBTRT</entity> will continue to
                        work toward greater inclusion within our association and professional
                        community in whatever capacity it can.</p>

                    <p><entity type="organization" identity="self">The GLBTRT</entity> also calls on
                            <entity type="organization">the American Library Association</entity> to
                        be more proactive and transparent in reporting instances of racism,
                        bullying, and discrimination and the action taken to address these
                        instances, to review and reinforce its code of conduct at all levels of the
                        organization, and to provide opportunities for all members to participate in
                        this review.</p>
                </body>

                <back>
                    <div type="pub_note">
                        <l>Posted on behalf of the GLBTRT Executive Board.</l>
                    </div>
                </back>

            </text>

            <text
                source="https://litablog.org/2019/02/litas-statement-in-response-to-incidents-at-ala-midwinter-2019/">

                <front>
                    <docTitle focus="incidents" context="alamw19">LITA’s Statement in Response to
                        Incidents at ALA Midwinter 2019</docTitle>
                    <div type="pub_note">
                        <l>February 4, 2019 * Jenny Levine</l>
                    </div>
                </front>

                <body>
                    <p>The <entity type="organization" identity="self">Library and Information
                            Technology Association (LITA)</entity> Board of Directors is aware that
                        there were several reports on social media from attendees who encountered
                        aggressive behavior, racism, and harassment at <entity type="event">the 2019
                            ALA Midwinter Meeting</entity>, which violated our values of diversity,
                        equity, and inclusion, and that there were multiple incident reports filed,
                        including one formal complaint regarding the violation of the Code of
                        Conduct as well. We thank those who were able to share their experiences and
                        draw attention to the systemic issues that our society and profession face.
                        As an association with an unwavering commitment to the values of diversity,
                        equity, and inclusion, <entity type="organization" identity="self"
                            >LITA</entity> believes that clear action is necessary and seeks
                        partnerships within <entity type="organization">ALA</entity> and beyond to
                        address these issues of systematic oppression.</p>

                    <p>It is our belief that safety, both physical and psychological, is a
                        requirement for the full engagement of participants. <entity
                            type="organization" identity="self">LITA</entity> is committed to
                        ensuring, through policy and action, that the culture and activities of
                            <entity type="organization" identity="self">LITA</entity> and <entity
                            type="organization">ALA</entity> are safe and productive. We are
                        therefore in agreement with the numerous expressions of concern and call for
                            <entity type="organization">ALA</entity> to step up in leading our
                        association and its members through the difficult but necessary work of
                        dismantling system oppression within the profession, understanding
                        differences, valuing those differences, and ultimately, learning how to
                        communicate and innovate in an inclusive manner that welcomes diverse
                        perspectives.</p>

                    <p><entity type="organization" identity="self">LITA</entity> believes that
                        education is a key component of this work. For this reason, we have decided
                        to commit funds to the creation and dissemination of free bystander/allyship
                        webinars. In collaboration with other units of <entity type="organization"
                            >ALA</entity>, we will develop trainings that we hope will equip <entity
                            type="organization" identity="self">LITA</entity> members with tools
                        that empower active and effective allyship, recognize and undo oppressive
                        behaviors and systems, and promote the practice of cultural humility,
                        thereby collectively increasing our collaborative capacity.</p>

                    <p>As always, <entity type="organization" identity="self">LITA</entity> stands
                        committed to the values of diversity, equity, and inclusion and welcomes
                        opportunities to collaborate and partner with <entity type="organization"
                            >ALA</entity> and beyond in order to realize these values fully. We
                        thank the <entity type="organization">ALA</entity> Executive Board and
                            <entity type="organization">REFORMA</entity> for crafting an appropriate
                        statement about racism and discrimination in the Library profession.</p>
                </body>

                <back>
                    <div type="pub_note">
                        <head>LITA Board of Directors</head>
                        <p>Bohyun Kim (President), Emily Morton-Owens (President-Elect), Andromeda
                            Yelton (Past-President), Lindsay Cronk, Tabatha Farney, Amanda L.
                            Goodman, Margaret Heller, Topher Lawton, Evviva Weinraub, Berika
                            Williams, Aaron Dobbs (LITA Division Councilor), Jodie Gambill, Brian
                            Rennick, Mark Beatty (ALA), Jenny Levine (ALA) </p>
                        <head>LITA Diversity &amp; Inclusion Committee</head>
                        <p>Jennifer Brown (Chair), Paula Jharina Pascual (Vice-Chair), Melissa
                            Stoner (Past-Chair), TJ Lamanna, Rebecca Marrall, Ted Quiballo, Jennifer
                            Vinopal</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="tags">
                        <l>2019 * alamw19, diversity, inclusion, racism</l>
                    </div>
                </back>

            </text>

            <text
                source="https://rusaupdate.org/2019/02/rusa-statement-against-racism-discrimination-and-harassment-in-the-profession/">

                <front>
                    <div type="pub_note">
                        <l>By Reference and User Services Association * February 5, 2019</l>
                    </div>
                    <docTitle focus="racism" context="profession">RUSA Statement Against Racism,
                        Discrimination, and Harassment in the Profession</docTitle>
                    <div type="pub_note">
                        <l>February 5, 2019</l>
                    </div>
                </front>

                <body>
                    <p>The <entity type="organization" identity="self">Reference and User Services
                            Association (RUSA)</entity> Board of Directors has learned of racist,
                        discriminatory, and harassing behavior at <entity type="event">2019 ALA
                            Midwinter Meeting</entity> in <entity type="place">Seattle, WA</entity>.
                        We would like to express our support to those who were harassed and
                        discriminated against during this particular incident and to all those who
                        have lived and worked too long in unsafe environments.</p>

                    <p>We would also like to renew our commitment to our statement on Equity,
                        Diversity, and Inclusion and call upon <entity type="organization"
                            >ALA</entity> Executive Committee to quickly respond, reassess, and
                        renew its commitment to their fourth strategic direction, through education
                        and advocacy for our colleagues and our patrons.</p>

                    <p>It is more important than ever that we as <entity type="organization"
                            identity="self">RUSA</entity> and as librarians and library staff work
                        on addressing the pervasive privilege and bias within our profession and
                        association. It is our responsibility to continue this work so that we can
                        continue to ensure “the right of access to information for people of all
                        identities, backgrounds, ages, and abilities especially with regard to
                        marginalized peoples.”</p>
                </body>

            </text>

            <text
                source="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1R7jnzEI9wRlGplx9s3bvH5xr4Hw_qzH38fuu1qcUrfw/edit">

                <front>
                    <docTitle focus="violations" context="alamw19">Open letter to ACRL Digital
                        Scholarship Section addressing racial aggression at Midwinter</docTitle>
                    <div type="pub_note">
                        <l>SUBJECT: Open letter addressing racialized aggression at Midwinter</l>
                        <l>DATE: Monday, February 4, 2019</l>
                        <l>TO: dss-l@lists.ala.org</l>
                        <l>Dear Digital Scholarship Section members and friends,</l>
                    </div>
                </front>

                <body>
                    <p>Many of you know about the incident of racialized aggression<link
                            target="https://aprilhathcock.wordpress.com/2019/01/30/alamw-what-happened-and-what-should-happen-next"
                        /> that <entity type="person" identity="named">April Hathcock</entity>
                        experienced during the <entity type="event">2019 ALA Midwinter
                            Meeting</entity> in <entity type="place">Seattle</entity>. She was not
                        alone; others, too, shared experiences of aggression during <entity
                            type="organization">ALA</entity> events, this <entity type="event"
                            >Midwinter</entity> and earlier. These harmful experiences by people of
                        color continue to be endemic to our profession and our professional
                        associations.</p>

                    <p>In response, the <entity type="organization">ALA</entity> Executive
                            Board<link
                            target="http://www.ala.org/news/member-news/2019/01/ala-executive-board-releases-statement-regarding-incident-council-forum"
                        />, the <entity type="organization">ACRL</entity> Board<link
                            target="https://www.acrl.ala.org/acrlinsider/archives/17145"/>, and
                            <entity type="organization">REFORMA</entity><link
                            target="https://www.reforma.org/statement-against-racism"/> (a <entity
                            type="protected_group">Latinx</entity> affiliate of <entity
                            type="organization">ALA</entity>) have released statements condemning
                        racism, harassment, and discrimination within the profession. Additionally,
                        two <entity type="organization">ALA</entity> Councilors, <entity
                            type="person" identity="named">Erin Stahlberg (ALCTS Councilor)</entity>
                        and <entity type="person" identity="named">Martin Garnar (IFRT
                            Councilor)</entity> composed an open letter addressing racialized
                            aggression<link
                            target="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1Du9Zo5bDM0MXssrInskn8mZNsIhHybpONeBxxLKru1c/edit"
                        /> in <entity type="place">Seattle</entity>; both <entity
                            type="organization">ALA</entity> Councilors and non-councilors are
                        invited to sign.</p>

                    <p>We, the <entity type="organization" identity="self">Digital Scholarship
                            Section</entity> Executive Committee, are committed to cultivating an
                        anti-racist ethos across <entity type="organization" identity="self">the
                            section</entity>. We do not speak on behalf of <entity
                            type="organization">ACRL</entity> or <entity type="organization"
                            >ALA</entity>. Rather, we are communicating the steps we will take as
                        leaders within <entity type="organization" identity="self">the
                            section</entity> to enact our shared professional values.</p>

                    <p>We will commit our time slot for <entity type="program">the Digital
                            Scholarship Information Exchange</entity> at <entity type="event">ALA
                            Annual 2019</entity> to showcasing social justice work in <entity
                            type="functional_area">digital scholarship</entity>. We will hold a
                        virtual town hall to acknowledge the continuing impact of racism on
                        librarians and librarianship and organize collective action we can take to
                        create anti-racist communities within the section and across <entity
                            type="organization">ALA</entity>. Finally, we will arrange for training
                        on anti-oppressive meeting facilitation to incoming <entity
                            type="organization" identity="self">section</entity> committee chairs,
                        committee members, and discussion group conveners.</p>

                    <p>We also want to hear from you. How can <entity type="organization"
                            identity="self">the section</entity> take action to become the kind of
                        inclusive professional community each of us deserves? To share your thoughts
                        with all members of the <entity type="organization" identity="self"
                            >section</entity>’s Executive Committee, please write to <entity
                            type="organization" identity="self"
                            >dssexec-l-request@lists.ala.org</entity>
                        <link target="mailto:dssexec-l-request@lists.ala.org"/>. You may also reach
                        out to any of us individually.</p>

                    <p><entity type="organization" identity="self">The Digital Scholarship
                            Section</entity> was formed so that library workers engaged in <entity
                            type="functional_area">digital scholarship</entity> could see a place
                        for themselves within <entity type="organization">ALA</entity> and <entity
                            type="organization">ACRL</entity>. Together we must make sure that the
                            <entity type="organization" identity="self">section</entity> is a safe
                        and welcoming community for all of our members. Let’s get to work.</p>

                </body>

                <back>
                    <div type="contact">
                        <l>Sincerely,</l>
                        <l>Brianna Marshall, Chair, briannahmarshall@gmail.com</l>
                        <l>Hannah Scates Kettler, Vice-Chair, hannah-s-kettler@uiowa.edu</l>
                        <l>Chelcie Juliet Rowell, Secretary, chelcie.rowell@tufts.edu</l>
                        <l>Elisandro Cabada, Member-at-Large, cabada@illinois.edu </l>
                        <l>Alix Keener, Member-at-Large, alix.keener@gmail.com</l>
                    </div>
                </back>

            </text>

            <text source="http://acrlny.org/statement-of-support-concern-from-acrl-ny/">

                <front>
                    <docTitle focus="unspecified" context="unspecified">Statement of Support &amp;
                        Concern from ACRL/NY</docTitle>
                    <div type="pub_note">
                        <l>Posted on 01/31/2019 by Derek Stadler</l>
                    </div>
                </front>

                <body>
                    <p><entity type="organization" identity="self">The Greater Metropolitan New York
                            City Chapter of ACRL/NY</entity> voices our serious concern about the
                        reported verbal abuse of <entity type="person" identity="anonymous">one of
                            our chapter members</entity>, at <entity type="event">the Council Forum
                            at ALA midwinter</entity>.</p>

                    <p><entity type="organization" identity="self">ACRL/NY</entity> reasserts our
                        commitment to equity, diversity and inclusion at all meetings and events. We
                        have a zero-tolerance policy towards harassment or intimidating and
                        aggressive behavior. We strongly urge <entity type="organization"
                            >ALA</entity> to hold their <entity type="organization">Council</entity>
                        accountable to ensure a safe space for all who attend their conferences.</p>

                    <p>Incidents like these do not exist in a vacuum. We at <entity
                            type="organization" identity="self">ACRL/NY</entity> are committed to do
                        better by our community of librarians, and we insist that as our parent
                        organization <entity type="organization">ALA</entity> take leadership to do
                        the same.</p>
                </body>

                <back>
                    <div type="pub_note">
                        <l>The Executive Board of ACRL/NY</l>
                        <l>This entry was posted in News by Derek Stadler.</l>
                    </div>
                </back>

            </text>

            <text
                source="https://acrloregon.org/2019/01/31/statement-of-concern-about-racist-incidents-at-theala-midwinter-conference/">

                <front>
                    <docTitle focus="violations" context="alamw19">Statement of concern about racist
                        incidents at the ALA Midwinter Conference</docTitle>
                    <div type="pub_note">
                        <l>Posted on January 31, 2019 by ajabm</l>
                    </div>
                </front>

                <body>
                    <p><entity type="organization" identity="self">ACRL-Oregon</entity> would like
                        to echo and support the statement<link
                            target="http://acrlny.org/statement-of-support-concern-from-acrl-ny/"/>
                        sent earlier by <entity type="organization">ACRL/NY</entity> regarding the
                        reported verbal abuse of <entity type="person" identity="anonymous">their
                            member</entity> as well as to express concern about additional racist
                        incidents at <entity type="event">the ALA Midwinter Conference</entity> that
                        were reported on social media.</p>

                    <p><entity type="organization" identity="self">ACRL-Oregon</entity> affirms our
                        commitment to equity, diversity, and inclusion and would like to see <entity
                            type="organization">ALA</entity> uphold their commitment to creating
                        inclusive spaces throughout their conferences, including in programs, the
                        exhibit hall, social events, and governance meetings. While having a
                        Statement of Appropriate Conduct<link
                            target="http://www.ala.org/conferencesevents/statement_appropriate_conduct"
                        /> is critical to ensuring victims of harassment have recourse, what matters
                        most is how victims and the accused are treated in the investigative
                        process. That one victim felt that she was being silenced during the process
                        is concerning. Greater transparency should be provided to members of <entity
                            type="organization">ALA</entity>’s elected governance structures about
                        how reports are handled while respecting the privacy of those involved.</p>

                    <p>We appreciate the <entity type="organization">ACRL</entity> Executive Board’s
                            statement<link
                            target="https://www.acrl.ala.org/acrlinsider/archives/17145"/> and hope
                        that it will ensure that structures are in place to address equity issues
                        and limit racial trauma within our organization. We appreciate that both
                            <entity type="organization">ALA</entity> and <entity type="organization"
                            >ACRL</entity> are committed to providing anti-bias training for leaders
                        and hope that this is extended to staff as well.</p>

                    <p>While our profession is focused on serving our diverse communities, there is
                        a history in this country of libraries and librarians upholding racism. The
                        lack of diversity of our own profession reflects this. We can all do more to
                        confront racism in our libraries and professional organizations and <entity
                            type="organization" identity="self">ACRL-Oregon</entity> is committed to
                        this work as well.</p>
                </body>

                <back>
                    <div type="contact">
                        <l>The ACRL-Oregon Board</l>
                        <l>http://acrloregon.org</l>
                    </div>
                    <div type="tags">
                        <l>Filed under: announcements, conferences</l>
                    </div>
                </back>

            </text>

            <text
                source="https://www.arl.org/news/arl-news/4718-arl-affirms-commitment-to-advancing-diversity-equity-inclusion-#">

                <front>
                    <docTitle focus="edi" context="unspecified">Statement: ARL Affirms Commitment to
                        Advancing Diversity, Equity, Inclusion</docTitle>
                    <div type="contact">
                        <l>by Susan Gibbons, President | susan.gibbons@yale.edu | on February 01,
                            2019</l>
                    </div>
                    <div type="pub_note">
                        <l>Association of Research Libraries</l>
                    </div>
                </front>

                <body>
                    <p><entity type="organization" identity="self">The Association of Research
                            Libraries (ARL)</entity> asserts its commitment to diversity, equity,
                        and inclusion as core values of <entity type="organization" identity="self"
                            >the Association</entity>. This commitment is deeply embedded in the
                        mission of libraries and archives, and in the work we do as an
                        institutional-member organization called upon to provide leadership in key
                        issues and practices that define our profession.</p>

                    <p>The harassment and intimidation that occurred during the recent <entity
                            type="event">American Library Association (ALA) Midwinter
                            Meeting</entity> should be of grave concern to all in the profession and
                        in the broader society. These events telegraph that we, as a society and a
                        profession, are far from truly realizing the vision of racial equity that so
                        many desire and that must be a core principle if we are to be a just and
                        equitable society.</p>

                    <p><entity type="organization" identity="self">ARL</entity> affirms its
                        responsibility for providing resources and educating leaders in libraries
                        and archives about the systemic barriers to achieving racial equity. <entity
                            type="organization" identity="self">The Association</entity> recently
                        adopted a code of conduct<link
                            target="https://www.arl.org/about#codeofconduct"/> for our meetings and
                        interactions, and we commit to bystander/ally training for the Board of
                        Directors and staff to ensure that our meetings are welcoming, inclusive,
                        and free of harassment or intimidation.</p>

                    <p>We will use this stark reminder of injustice as an opportunity for discussion
                        and growth, so that we might strengthen our role in advancing equity and
                        inclusion for all in our association and in our profession.</p>
                </body>

                <back>
                    <div type="pub_note">
                        <head>About the Association of Research Libraries</head>
                        <p>The Association of Research Libraries (ARL) is a nonprofit organization
                            of 124 research libraries in Canada and the US<link
                                target="https://www.arl.org/membership#.WtTiDtPwbNB"/> whose mission
                            is to advance research, learning, and scholarly communication. The
                            Association fosters the open exchange of ideas and expertise, promotes
                            equity and diversity, and pursues advocacy and public policy efforts
                            that reflect the values of the library, scholarly, and higher education
                            communities. ARL forges partnerships and catalyzes the collective
                            efforts of research libraries to enable knowledge creation and to
                            achieve enduring and barrier-free access to information. ARL is on the
                            web at ARL.org<link target="http://www.arl.org/"/>.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="tags">
                        <l>Diversity, Statement</l>
                    </div>
                </back>

            </text>

            <text source="http://www.ala.org/pla/about/mission">

                <front>
                    <div type="pub_note">
                        <l>PLA Mission and Strategy</l>
                    </div>
                    <docTitle focus="edi" context="unspecified">PLA reaffirms commitment to equity,
                        diversity, inclusion, and social justice</docTitle>
                </front>

                <body>
                    <p>At the recent <entity type="event">Midwinter Meeting in Seattle</entity>,
                        there were reports of violations of <entity type="organization"
                        >ALA</entity>’s Code of Conduct and the <entity type="organization"
                            >ALA</entity> Executive Board has released this statement<link
                            target="http://www.ala.org/news/member-news/2019/01/ala-executive-board-releases-statement-regarding-incident-council-forum"
                        />.</p>

                    <p>Like <entity type="organization">ALA</entity>, <entity type="organization"
                            identity="self">PLA</entity> is committed to creating an inclusive
                        environment for all our members. In its 2018–2022 Strategic Plan<link
                            target="http://www.ala.org/pla/about/mission/strategicplan"/>, the
                            <entity type="organization" identity="self">PLA</entity> Board of
                        Directors affirmed its commitment to equity, diversity, inclusion and social
                        justice (EDISJ). This work requires persistent and vigilant efforts to speak
                        out and take action against oppression in <entity type="functional_area"
                            >public libraries</entity>, in society, and within the library
                        profession. To fully meet these goals, we must examine and test our systems
                        for acting when we fall short of our aspirations, acknowledge gaps and
                        shortcomings, and take action to do better. To this end, <entity
                            type="organization" identity="self">PLA</entity> commits to:</p>
                    <list>
                        <item>Supporting and participating in training and forums to address
                            systemic racism in professional associations;</item>
                        <item>Re-examining our own systems for developing and delivering inclusive
                            and respectful programs and events, and for responding in a timely and
                            transparent manner when incidents arise that violate the <entity
                                type="organization">ALA</entity> Code of Conduct;</item>
                        <item>Continuing and expanding training<link
                                target="http://www.ala.org/pla/education/inperson/equity"/> and
                            resources that support equity, diversity, inclusion and social justice
                            in <entity type="organization" identity="self">PLA</entity>, <entity
                                type="organization">ALA</entity> and our libraries;</item>
                        <item>Equipping our members<link
                                target="http://www.ala.org/pla/initiatives/edi"/> with tools,
                            mentoring/coaching, learning opportunities, and other resources to
                            advocate and apply EDISJ principles in their libraries and
                            communities.</item>
                    </list>

                    <p>Please join <entity type="organization" identity="self">PLA</entity> leaders
                        in reaffirming our commitment to equity, diversity, inclusion and advancing
                        social justice in our libraries, our communities, and our association. We
                        appreciate all your contributions and look forward to our work together.
                    </p>
                </body>

                <back>
                    <div type="contact">
                        <p>Please don’t hesitate to share any questions or thoughts with PLA at
                            pla@ala.org.</p>
                    </div>
                </back>

            </text>

            <text
                source="http://www.ala.org/news/press-releases/2019/02/alcts-statement-against-harassment-racism-and-discrimination-0">

                <front>
                    <docTitle focus="racism" context="unspecified">ALCTS Statement Against
                        Harassment, Racism and Discrimination</docTitle>
                    <div type="pub_note">
                        <l>For Immediate Release</l>
                        <l>Mon, 02/11/2019</l>
                    </div>
                    <div type="contact">
                        <head>Contact:</head>
                        <l>Brooke Morris-Chott</l>
                        <l>Program Officer, Communications</l>
                        <l>ALCTS</l>
                        <l>bmorris@ala.org</l>
                    </div>
                    <div type="pub_note">
                        <l>CHICAGO—</l>
                    </div>
                </front>

                <body>
                    <p>In light of reports of incidents of harassing, discriminatory and racist
                        behavior that occurred at <entity type="event">the 2019 American Library
                            Association Midwinter Meeting</entity>, the <entity type="organization"
                            identity="self">Association for Library Collections and Technical
                            Services (ALCTS)</entity> Board offers its support to the individuals
                        who were the targets of such behavior and affirms the statement from the
                            <entity type="organization">ALA</entity> Executive Board<link
                            target="http://www.ala.org/news/member-news/2019/01/ala-executive-board-releases-statement-regarding-incident-council-forum"
                        /> in its denunciation of such behavior, as well as its call to uphold
                            <entity type="organization">ALA</entity>’s Statement of Appropriate
                            Conduct<link
                            target="http://www.ala.org/conferencesevents/statement_appropriate_conduct"
                        />.</p>

                    <p>In particular, <entity type="organization" identity="self">ALCTS</entity>
                        supports the goals in the Executive Board Statement to provide resources and
                        training on equity, diversity and inclusion for all members and to apply a
                        social justice framework to the <entity type="organization">ALA</entity>
                        Strategic Directions. We hope to work with <entity type="organization"
                            >ALA</entity> to strengthen and improve the Statement of Appropriate
                        Conduct and ensure its enforcement. <entity type="organization"
                            identity="self">ALCTS</entity> also recognizes that words are not enough
                        for this situation and must be transformed into action.</p>

                    <p><entity type="organization" identity="self">ALCTS</entity> will review its
                        own activities, both online and in-person, to determine what changes should
                        be made to bring our actions in line with our rhetoric. <entity
                            type="organization" identity="self">ALCTS</entity> is engaged in
                        supporting equity, diversity and inclusion initiatives through work such as
                        developing a code of ethics for <entity type="functional_area"
                            >cataloging</entity>, supporting the <entity type="functional_area"
                            >preservation</entity> needs of cultural heritage institutions through
                            <entity type="program">Preservation in Action</entity>, providing grants
                        for library professionals from developing countries to attend <entity
                            type="organization" identity="self">ALCTS</entity> online courses,
                        supporting <entity type="organization">ALA</entity> Spectrum Scholars, and
                        providing people from underrepresented groups with awards to attend <entity
                            type="event">the ALA Annual Conference</entity>. Our current activities,
                        however, are just a starting point. Our new strategic plan, currently in
                        draft form, includes explicit support for equity, diversity and inclusion as
                        a core objective, promulgating the importance of EDI to all levels and
                        activities within <entity type="organization" identity="self"
                        >ALCTS</entity>. <entity type="organization" identity="self">ALCTS</entity>
                        will invest financial resources to put the commitments of the <entity
                            type="organization" identity="self">ALCTS</entity> strategic plan and
                        this statement into action. We believe in the adage that every budget is a
                        moral document—it is both practically and symbolically important that we put
                        money behind our work in this area.</p>

                    <p>Education and empowerment are key components of the work going forward. We
                        will highlight the Statement of Appropriate Conduct at all <entity
                            type="organization" identity="self">ALCTS</entity> meetings, we will
                        ensure that participants are able to contact designated <entity
                            type="organization" identity="self">ALCTS</entity> EDI resource
                        representatives in case of conduct violations, and we will provide training
                        to <entity type="organization" identity="self">ALCTS</entity> leaders to
                        help them become skilled meeting facilitators who can intercede when
                        behavior becomes problematic. In addition to strengthening <entity
                            type="organization" identity="self">our own division</entity>’s support
                        for EDI, we will pursue collaborations and partnerships with other <entity
                            type="organization">ALA</entity> divisions and offices in support of
                        these goals, including working with <entity type="organization"
                            >LITA</entity> and <entity type="organization">LLAMA</entity> to develop
                        bystander/allyship webinars and other training.</p>

                    <p><entity type="organization" identity="self">ALCTS</entity> remains committed
                        to improving equity, diversity and inclusion within the profession and
                        within <entity type="organization" identity="self">the Association</entity>
                        and to eliminating incidents of harassment, racism and discrimination. This
                        statement serves to reaffirm and redouble our efforts in this area.</p>
                </body>

                <back>
                    <div type="about">
                        <p>The Association for Library Collections &amp; Technical Services
                                (ALCTS)<link target="http://www.ala.org/alcts"/> is the national
                            association for information providers who work in collections and
                            technical services, such as acquisitions, cataloging, collection
                            development, preservation and continuing resources in digital and print
                            formats. ALCTS is a division of the American Library Association.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="tags">
                        <l>Association for Library Collections and Technical Svcs</l>
                    </div>
                </back>

            </text>

            <text
                source="https://connect.ala.org/communities/community-home/digestviewer/viewthread?MessageKey=156b010c-2106-4f27-a5b5-11b19add534c">

                <front>
                    <docTitle focus="incidents" context="alamw19">STATEMENT ON ALA MID-WINTER
                        INCIDENT</docTitle>
                    <div type="pub_note">
                        <l>Posted Feb 08, 2019 02:34 PM</l>
                        <l>Adam Szczepaniak</l>
                    </div>
                </front>

                <body>
                    <p> The <entity type="organization" identity="self">Association of Specialized,
                            Government, and Cooperative Library Agencies (ASGCLA)</entity> Executive
                        Committee is troubled by reports of racist, discriminatory, and harassing
                        behavior at <entity type="event">the 2019 ALA Midwinter Meeting</entity> in
                            <entity type="place">Seattle, WA</entity>. We support those who
                        experienced harassment or discrimination at <entity type="event">the ALA
                            Meeting</entity>. We recognize that many in our profession have been
                        marginalized, unrecognized, or put in intimidating environments. We believe
                        that everyone needs to be heard and respected.</p>

                    <p>
                        <entity type="organization" identity="self">ASGCLA</entity> includes in its
                        area of responsibility, service to <entity type="protected_group">persons
                            facing barriers to library use that are both visible and
                            invisible</entity>. <entity type="organization" identity="self"
                            >ASGCLA</entity> affirms <entity type="organization">ALA</entity>'s
                        fourth strategic direction of equity, diversity and inclusion, and the
                        priorities set in the Equity Diversity and Inclusion Implementation
                            Plan<link
                            target="http://www.ala.org/aboutala/sites/ala.org.aboutala/files/content/diversity/EDI-SD-Implementation-FINAL.pdf"
                        />. <entity type="organization" identity="self">ASGCLA</entity> urges
                            <entity type="organization">ALA</entity> Management and the Executive
                        Board to take quick action and provide leadership for the profession through
                        education and advocacy. </p>

                    <p>
                        <entity type="organization" identity="self">ASGCLA</entity>, <entity
                            type="organization">ALA</entity>, and the library profession must
                        prioritize efforts to increase inclusion and respect for everyone. We are
                        committed to supporting and acting on changes needed to make our profession
                        and association truly inclusive. </p>
                </body>

                <back>
                    <div type="contact">
                        <l>Adam Szczepaniak</l>
                        <l>Deputy State Librarian &amp; Director</l>
                        <l>New Jersey State Library - Talking Book and Braille Center</l>
                    </div>
                </back>

            </text>

            <text source="https://www.llama.ala.org/llamaleads/?p=2848">

                <front>
                    <docTitle focus="incidents" context="alamw19">LLAMA Board Initial Response to
                        MW19 Incidents</docTitle>
                </front>

                <body>
                    <p>For members who are not aware of recent incidents of harassment at <entity
                            type="event">the ALA Midwinter Meeting</entity> in <entity type="place"
                            >Seattle</entity>, <entity type="organization" identity="self">the
                            Library Leadership and Management Association (LLAMA)</entity> would
                        like to call attention to the <entity type="organization">ALA</entity>
                        Executive Board’s response<link
                            target="http://www.ala.org/news/member-news/2019/01/ala-executive-board-releases-statement-regarding-incident-council-forum"
                        />.</p>

                    <p>As <entity type="organization" identity="self">our division</entity> name
                        implies, we recognize we have a obligation to model supportive and
                        respectful <entity type="functional_area">leadership</entity> across the
                        entire organization. <entity type="organization" identity="self"
                            >LLAMA</entity> affirms the efforts of <entity type="organization"
                            >ALA</entity> to uphold the Statement of Appropriate Conduct, and
                        recognizes we have much to do to improve equity, diversity, and inclusion
                        within <entity type="organization">ALA</entity>. <entity type="organization"
                            identity="self">LLAMA</entity> members know how important it is both for
                            <entity type="organization" identity="self">our division</entity> and
                        for our home institutions to combat bias, racism and harassment, so that
                        through our organizations, we can all provide the best library or
                        information services possible. <entity type="organization" identity="self"
                            >LLAMA</entity> will continue to emphasize the <entity
                            type="functional_area">leadership and management</entity> competencies
                        that support safe, supportive workplaces — Communication skills, Emotional
                        intelligence, Ethics, Conflict management, Diversity consciousness,
                        Professionalism and Self awareness — and will seek opportunities to make
                        sure all our members feel this is their organization.</p>
                </body>

                <back>
                    <div type="contact">
                        <l>Lynn Hoffman</l>
                        <l>President, Library Leadership and Management Association (LLAMA)</l>
                        <l>Director of Operations, Somerset County Library System of NJ</l>
                    </div>
                    <div type="tags">
                        <l>Explore posts in the same categories: ALA Updates, LLAMA Leadership</l>
                    </div>
                </back>

            </text>

        </group>
    </text>
</document>